<?xml version='1.0' encoding='UTF-8'?>
<component type="desktop-application">
  <!--
  SPDX-License-Identifier: CC0-1.0
  SPDX-FileCopyrightText: No copyright
  -->
  <id>@app_id@</id>
  <metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
  <project_license>GPL-3.0-or-later</project_license>
  <name translatable="no" translate="no">Cartero</name>
  <summary>Make HTTP requests and test APIs</summary>
  <launchable type="desktop-id">@app_id@.desktop</launchable>
  <description>
    <p>Cartero is a graphical HTTP client that can be used as a developer tool to test web APIs and perform all kind of HTTP requests to web servers. It is compatible with any REST, SOAP or XML-RPC API and it supports multiple request methods as well as attaching body payloads to compatible requests.</p>
    <p>Features:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Loads and saves to plain Git-friendly TOML files, so that you can own your data.</li>
      <li>Customization and modification of the request headers and body payloads.</li>
      <li>Variable binding for API keys and other secret information.</li>
    </ul>
  </description>
  <screenshots>
    <screenshot type="default">
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/danirod/cartero/trunk/data/screenshots/cartero-default.png</image>
      <caption>Main window of Cartero</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/danirod/cartero/trunk/data/screenshots/cartero-headers.png</image>
      <caption>Modifying HTTP headers</caption>
    </screenshot>
    <screenshot>
      <image>https://raw.githubusercontent.com/danirod/cartero/trunk/data/screenshots/cartero-payload.png</image>
      <caption>Setting the request payload</caption>
    </screenshot>
  </screenshots>
  <recommends>
    <control>keyboard</control>
    <control>pointing</control>
    <display_length compare="ge">480</display_length>
  </recommends>
  <url type="homepage">https://cartero.danirod.es</url>
  <url type="vcs-browser">https://github.com/danirod/cartero</url>
  <url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/danirod/cartero/issues</url>
  <url type="help">https://cartero.danirod.es/docs</url>
  <url type="translate">https://hosted.weblate.org/projects/cartero/cartero/</url>
  <url type="donation">https://ko-fi.com/danirod</url>
  <developer_name translatable="no" translate="no">Dani Rodríguez</developer_name>
  <developer id="com.github.danirod">
    <name translatable="no" translate="no">Dani Rodríguez</name>
  </developer>
  <update_contact>dani@danirod.es</update_contact>
  <content_rating type="oars-1.0"/>
  <translation type="gettext">cartero</translation>
  <branding>
    <color scheme_preference="light" type="primary">#edf0f1</color>
    <color scheme_preference="dark" type="primary">#465563</color>
  </branding>
  <releases>
    <release date="2026-01-25" version="26.0">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added a color scheme selector for the code views.</li>
          <li>Added application window theming and tinting.</li>
          <li>Added a menu option to duplicate requests.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The response pane will now render the effective URL of a response.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to reveal the values of .env variables in the endpoint pane.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Responses were being treated as binary if they contained the CR (\r) character.</li>
          <li>Disabling TLS validation still failed a request if the certificate didn't have a matching SAN.</li>
          <li>MacOS: the main application window could sometimes stop receiving mouse clicks on macOS 26.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Basque</li>
          <li>Indonesian</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
          <li>Chinese (Simplified)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-11-14" version="25.0">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added support for proxies.</li>
          <li>Added support for dotenv files: values defined in an .env file can be loaded as variables.</li>
          <li>The Headers pane will now present pre-generated headers added by Cartero.</li>
          <li>Added a new request body type: "From file", loads the raw request body from the contents of a file.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to export requests in JetBrains HTTP format.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to export a request or a response directly into a file.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to export the contents of an HTTP response.</li>
          <li>The welcome pane now has an additional sheet with information and links.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The Export tab has moved to a dropdown menu in the window toolbar.</li>
          <li>Opening a new endpoint will automatically focus the URL entry field.</li>
          <li>Disabled variables, headers or parameters will now render slightly dimmed.</li>
          <li>When multiple variables or headers with the same key are present, those who will be ignored be marked.</li>
          <li>Showing or concealing passwords in basic auth or bearer token fields will now be remembered in the application state.</li>
          <li>The settings dialog has a new look and feel, using split windows.</li>
          <li>Responses with a binary body (like images or videos or octet-streams) will suggest saving the response into a file rather than rendering it in the code view.</li>
          <li>The default user agent used in HTTP request has changed to "Cartero/25.0 (isahc/1.7.2 curl/8.12.1-DEV)" (version numbers will bump as future releases flow).</li>
          <li>The responsiveness of the application will behave better on small windows and mobile devices.</li>
          <li>Dependencies bumped: Cartero now requires at least GNOME SDK 46 to build the app.</li>
          <li>Windows: the application look and feel on Windows 11 now uses the acrilyic look and feel.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>HTTP responses sometimes were not rendered if they had the Content-Type header set to JSON but they were not actually parseable as JSON.</li>
          <li>HTTP response headers sometimes did not render properly when they had angle brackets (such as the Link header).</li>
          <li>HTTP requests sometimes could not be exported when they had spaces in the URL.</li>
          <li>Windows: overriding the language in the settings dialog previously had no effect.</li>
          <li>MacOS: the URL bar did not focus when pressing Command-L.</li>
          <li>MacOS: the export dialog did not actually copy the code to the system clipboard.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Czech</li>
          <li>German</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>Basque</li>
          <li>Galician</li>
          <li>Indonesian</li>
          <li>Portuguese</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-08-10" version="0.2.4">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Pressing the Tab or the Shift-Tab keys in a request table (parameters, variables...) will now skip the row itself and focus instead an actual component like the checkbox or the dropdown menu.</li>
          <li>MacOS: on systems with a dual graphics card setup, Cartero will now run on the integrated rather than the discrete one. (This is good, it will save a lot of battery.)</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed accessibility issues: missing labels and tooltips within some window widgets.</li>
          <li>Some keyboard shortcuts were not being described by thee Keyboard Shortcuts help dialog.</li>
          <li>The dropdown menu for the request method had the wrong appearance when the computer uses a right-to-left layout (such as Arabic or Hebrew).</li>
          <li>MacOS: Zoom in, zoom out, zoom reset and search keyboard shortcuts for code views were using the wrong keyboard modifiers.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>French</li>
          <li>Galician</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-07-05" version="0.2.3">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Exporting a request as cURL did not include the request payload when the type is XML.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Catalan</li>
          <li>German</li>
          <li>Basque</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-04-30" version="0.2.2">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The URL field will be less laggy when the URL has query parameters, thanks to a performance increase in how query params are reflected in the table in the Parameters tab.</li>
          <li>Windows, macOS, AppImage: updated vendored runtime to GTK 4.18.4.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The query params table did not reflect the query params when the address in the URL field started with a variable.</li>
          <li>Fields modified in the query parameters table will not be rendered url-encoded in the URL field, as they used to.</li>
          <li>Requests will not fail anymore if they have a disabled header that references an undefined variable.</li>
          <li>GNU/Linux: fixed an application crash if gsettings-desktop-schemas is not available.</li>
          <li>macOS: the save dialog will not present two extensions in the initial file name in macOS Sequoia.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Czech</li>
          <li>German</li>
          <li>Basque</li>
          <li>Portuguese</li>
          <li>Tamil</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-04-03" version="0.2.1">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Disabled variables in the variables table were still being picked</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Catalan</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>Galician</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-03-21" version="0.2.0">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>An authorization tab, currently supporting basic authentication and bearer tokens.</li>
          <li>A Cancel button to stop an HTTP request in progress.</li>
          <li>An error panel to report errors related to a failing web request.</li>
          <li>Alert dialogs to report errors related to loading and saving files.</li>
          <li>New keyboard shortcuts and mouse gestures for zooming text views.</li>
          <li>Improved the about dialog.</li>
          <li>Windows, MacOS and AppImage: a software update checker has been added to the settings dialog.</li>
          <li>MacOS: added a menu bar for quick access to the application commands.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Application errors will now properly report the cause of an error and not just generic messages.</li>
          <li>During a request, the application will now stay clickable and not freeze.</li>
          <li>Units for the response size will now be internationalized (for instance, 32.4 Ko rather than 32.4 kB when running in French).</li>
          <li>Reduced the precission of the response duration indicator to prevent confusion.</li>
          <li>Disabled query params in the Parameters table will now be persisted into the file.</li>
          <li>Simplified the application icon and updated the branding.</li>
          <li>MacOS and Windows: the default application font will now be larger.</li>
          <li>MacOS: the window now uses an integrated title bar like the GNU/Linux version.</li>
          <li>Windows: cartero.exe now uses the application icon for the executable file.</li>
          <li>Windows: require Windows 10 or newer to install the application.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Requests whose URL do not start with http:// or https:// (such as "localhost:3000/users") should not fail now.</li>
          <li>During prettification of JSON responses, objects were being sorted; they will respect the original order now.</li>
          <li>The headers and variables tables lost the ability to report when a field name was duplicated.</li>
          <li>Disabled query params in the Parameters table were lost when the request URL changed.</li>
          <li>Windows: closing the settings dialog sometimes buried the Cartero main window under other windows.</li>
          <li>Windows: the title bar stayed in light mode even when the application ran in dark mode.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Catalan</li>
          <li>Czech</li>
          <li>Esperanto</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>French</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
          <li>Romanian</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
          <li>Tamil</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-02-15" version="0.1.5">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Changed the error message when a request uses an unsupported protocol for clarity purposes.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Prevents tabs from becoming unresponsive if a request fails in certain conditions.</li>
          <li>Prevents requests from failing if they have a trailing or leading space.</li>
          <li>Requests whose URL start with a variable (bound to something that starts with http or https) can be made again.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Czech</li>
          <li>French</li>
          <li>Portuguese (Brazil)</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2025-01-26" version="0.1.4">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Sending an HTTP request failed if the protocol was not specified.</li>
          <li>Pre-compiled versions for Windows were not signed.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Czech</li>
          <li>French</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2024-12-23" version="0.1.3">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Added a tab to generate a cURL command with the contents of a request.</li>
          <li>Added a preferences dialog to control application settings.</li>
          <li>Added a search functionality (Ctrl-F) to the text area panes.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>It is now possible to disable validation of TLS certificates.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to follow redirections when making HTTP requests.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to configure a timeout for the HTTP request.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to customize the font used for the text area panes.</li>
          <li>It is now possible to customize the light or dark appearance of the application.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fixed the HTTP response label sometimes having the wrong semantic color.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Catalan</li>
          <li>Esperanto</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>Romanian</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
          <li>Tamil</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2024-10-11" version="0.1.2">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>This is a minor release that addresses some issues and fixes some things found.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>It is now possible to open multiple files using the dialog picker.</li>
          <li>Translation updates: Russian</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Fix translation for the about and shortcuts dialog.</li>
          <li>Word wrapping of long lines without spaces did not work properly.</li>
          <li>Deactivate toolbar buttons if no request are open.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>Russian</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2024-07-30" version="0.1.1">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>This is a minor release that addresses some issues and small changes found in the last couple of days. It accepts feedback from the community and even some pull requests received in the last days.</p>
        <p>Changed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Pressing the Enter key while focusing the request URL entry will now send the HTTP request</li>
          <li>The response body page is now the default page for the response notebook</li>
          <li>The HTTP status code will now use semantic colors to report the status code category (success, client error, server error...)</li>
          <li>Provided a Metainfo file for submission into Flathub</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Fixed:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>The application may not open files when running as a Flatpak in sandbox mode</li>
          <li>The Nix flake did not build due to some missing dependencies</li>
          <li>Clicking on any link on Microsoft Windows did not open the default web browser</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Catalan</li>
          <li>Esperanto</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
          <li>Romanian</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
    <release date="2024-07-26" version="0.1.0">
      <description translatable="no" translate="no">
        <p>Initial release. I've crafted a MVP that consolidates the most important features to start using Cartero. Some features has been delayed for a future release, but there is already enough features for it to be useful.</p>
        <p>Added:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>A fully functional HTTP client with support for multiple request methods, and payload types.</li>
          <li>A variable engine that allows to move things such as API keys, passwords or hostnames into a variable that can be injected later into the URL or other headers.</li>
          <li>File support to load and store requests for a future session.</li>
        </ul>
        <p>Translation Updates:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>Esperanto</li>
          <li>Spanish</li>
        </ul>
      </description>
    </release>
  </releases>
</component>
